Register of the Federation of Russian Charitable Organizations of the United States Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Federation of Russian Charitable Organizations of the United States (Federatsiia Russkikh Blagotvoritelnykh Organizatsii) records,
1947-1963
2000C88
Federation of Russian Charitable Organizations of the United States
13 microfilm reels. (1.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, minutes, financial records, reports, and lists, relating to resettlement of Russian refugees in the United States and Australia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of the Federation of Russian Charitable Organizations, whose primary purpose was to assist in the immigration of Russian displaced persons from the Far East and Europe to the United States and Australia following the Second World War. The collection was originally arranged by the organization's director, Anatolii Stefanovich Loukashkin, and his classification has been retained. The records include the organization's predecessors and affiliates, e.g. The Committee of Russian Charitable Organizations of Northern California, Russian Orthodox Churches Relief Fund, and Russko-Amerikanskii soiuz zashchity i pomoshchi russkim vne Rossii (aka Russian-American Union).
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russians--United States.; Russians--Australia.; Refugees.; Russia.; United States.; Australia.; International relief.
Series Description
- Office File, 1947-1963. (Box 1-11)
  Clippings, correspondence, financial records, minutes of meetings, reports and other documents, arranged by physical form
- Memorabilia, n.d. (Box 11)
  Stamp of the Russian Orthodox Churches Relief Fund
- Closed File, 1948-1958. (Box 12-13)
  Confidential materials, immigration lists and registration book, arranged alphabetically by physical form. Closed to researchers due to restrictions
Container List
- OFFICE FILE, 1947-1963 (Box 1)
  - Administrative Section file.
    Includes charter, founding documents, correspondence, activity reports and bulletins, lists of members, minutes of meetings
    - General
      - 1948-1950 (Folder 1: 1)
      - 1950-1958 (Folder 1: 2)
      - 1950-1959 (Folder 1: 3-4)
    - Materials collected by A. S. Loukashkin as representative of Russian Center, San Francisco, and as Executive Director
      - General
        - 1951-1953 (Folder 1: 5)
        - 1953-1958 (Box-folder 2: 1)
      - Correspondence
        - General
          - 1953-1958 (Folder 2: 2-4)
          - 1959-1960 (Folder 2: 5)
        - Savva, Archbishop of Sydney, Australia, and New Zealand, 1958-1963., See also Subject file/Refugees, Russian/Correspondence (Folder 2: 6)
          Includes materials related to the liquidation of the Russian Orthodox Churches Relief Fund.
      - Report of a trip to Washington, DC, 1953 June 5. (Folder 2: 7)
        Includes copy of Loukashkin's statement before the Subcommittee of the Committee on the Judiciary, United States Senate, 1953 May 27
    - Official documents of the U.S. government and its agencies, as well as other international relief and non-governmental organizations. (Box-folder 3: 1)
      Includes bulletins, circulars, forms, memoranda, reports and other matter, 1953-1957
    - Section 6 case file, 1957-1960 (Folder 3: 2)
  - Assurance procurement contracts, 1955-1957 (Folder 3: 3)
  - Clippings, 1950-1962 (Folder 3: 4)
  - Financial records
    - Cash reports, 1950-1957 (Folder 3: 5)
    - Membership fees, 1950-1957 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Monthly reports (Box 4)
      - Loguinoff, E. C., 1954-1957 (Folder 4: 1)
      - Loukashkin, A. S., 1954-1957 (Folder 4: 2)
    - Receipt books
      - 1956 (Folder 4: 3)
      - 1957 March-July (Folder 4: 4)
      - 1957 August-1958 November (Folder 4: 5)
    - Receipts
      - 1955 January-June (Folder 5: 1)
      - 1955 July-December (Folder 5: 2)
      - 1956 January-June (Folder 5: 3)
      - 1956 July-December (Folder 5: 4)
      - 1961 January-December (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Savings account statements, 1957-1961 (Folder 6: 2)
    - Statements of receipts and expenses
      - 1955-1961 (Folder 6: 3)
      - 1957-1961 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Tax records, 1960-1961 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Miscellany, 1958-1962 (Folder 6: 6)
  - Minutes of meetings
    - 1950-1954 (Folder 6: 7)
    - 1955-1957 (Folder 6: 8)
    - 1957-1958 (Folder 6: 9)
  - Reception service file (Box 7)
    - 1955 (Folder 7: 1)
    - 1956
      - January-July (Folder 7: 2)
      - July-December (Folder 7: 3)
    - 1957
      - January (Folder 7: 4)
      - February-July (Folder 7: 5)
    - 1958 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - 1959
      - January-March (Folder 8: 2)
      - April-October (Folder 8: 3)
    - 1960 (Folder 8: 4)
  - Registration lists., See CLOSED FILE
  - Reports (Folder 8: 5)
  - Subject file (Box 9)
    - Church World Service
      - 1958 (Folder 9: 1)
      - 1959 (Folder 9: 2)
      - 1960 (Folder 9: 3)
    - Komitet russkikh blagotvoritelnykh organizatsii severnoi Kalifornii. Bulletins, 1947 (Folder 9: 4)
    - Refugees, Chinese. (Folder 9: 5)
      Includes correspondence, passenger lists, printed matter, 1955-1957
    - Refugees, Russian.
      Includes clippings, correspondence, photographs, reports, and other materials on position of Russians in China and the Far East and possibility of their migration to North and South America and Australia
      - Clippings, 1951-1957 (Folder 9: 6)
      - Clippings, 1951-1957 (Box-folder 10: 1)
      - Conference proceedings
        - "Pervoe Vsenarodnoe Sobranie v San Frantsisko," 1953 February 20 (Folder 10: 2)
        - "Vtoroe Vsenarodnoe sobranie v San Frantsisko," 1953 June 5 (Folder 10: 3)
      - Correspondence, 1957-1960. (Folder 10: 4-5)
        Includes appeals for financial or humanitarian aid, help in resettlement, etc.
      - Correspondence, 1957-1960 (Box-folder 11: 1)
      - Miscellany. (Folder 11: 2-3)
        Includes clippings, correspondence, reports and other materials, mainly on Russians in China and Manchuria, 1952-1958
    - Russko-Amerikanskii soiuz zashchity i pomoshchi russkim vne Rossii. (Folder 11: 4)
      Includes clippings, correspondence, petitions, reports and other materials, 1949-1953
    - Tubabao camp, Philippines, 1949-1952. (Folder 11: 5)
      Includes clippings, correspondence and reports
    - Miscellany. (Folder 11: 6)
      Includes appeal, business cards, information flyers, and documents relating to various other Russian émigré organizations. Also includes incomplete and anonymous report entitled "Die russische Gefangenschaft," 1947 June 16. Typescript
- MEMORABILIA, n.d., Not filmed (Folder 11: 7)
  Stamp of the Russian Orthodox Churches Relief Fund.
- CLOSED FILE, 1948-1958., This file is closed to researchers due to restrictions (Box 12)
  - Confidential file, 1956 (Folder 12: 1)
  - Immigration lists, 1948-1958 (Folder 12: 2-9)
  - Immigration lists, 1948-1958 (Box-folder 13: 1-2)
  - Registration book, n.d. (Folder 13: 3)